ETFs are no longer synonymous with
sensible investing. The fund management
industry is launching hundreds of new
actively managed ETFs every year. And
for the first time in US market history,
there are more ETFs than there are
individual stocks. And there are more
actively managed ETFs than there are
index tracking ETFs. Many of the ETFs
being launched today have been
engineered clearly to attract assets
rather than to improve outcomes for
investors. I think what we are seeing is
best described as ETF slop. I'm Ben
Felix, chief investment officer at PWL
Capital, and I'm going to tell you why
ETF SLOP is making it harder for
investors to make good long-term
decisions and bringing us right back to
the dark ages of investing.
2025 was a big year for ETFs in the US
market. More than 1,000 new ETFs were
launched, and the majority of those fund
launches were actively managed. That is
a record for new fund launches in a
year. Here in Canada, we had more than
300 new ETFs launch. Again, with the
majority being actively managed. Not
only are many of these funds actively
managed, but they're employing complex
strategies that I think are unlikely to
be beneficial for most investors most of
the time. While low fees have been a big
part of the success of ETFs, with many
index ETFs having fees below 0.1%,
the average management fee for US listed
ETFs launched in 2025 was more than
0.7%.
And 166 of the newly launched funds have
a management fee above 1%. Index ETFs
showed investors the light. You do not
need to pay high fees for actively
managed mutual funds that trail the
market. That caused real change with
investors ditching their high fee
actively managed funds for lowcost index
ETFs. This new wave of high fee ETFs is
bringing us right back toward darkness.
Let me back up. ETF stands for
exchangeraded fund. that is a fund that
trades on a stock exchange like a stock.
The first ETF was created here in Canada
and it was an index ETF tracking
Canadian large cap stocks. An ETF is
just a wrapper that can hold an
investment strategy inside of it, making
it easy to get exposure to that strategy
by investing in units of the fund. For
example, it's much easier to buy an S&P
500 ETF than it is to buy all of the
stocks in the S&P 500 index and make the
necessary trades to match changes in the
index over time. Think of it like buying
a pre-made fruit salad instead of
shopping for washing and chopping 500
different fruits yourself. I don't even
know if there are 500 fruits. While
index funds were the first use of the
ETF structure, ETFs can hold pretty much
any investment strategy. Even complex
strategies using leverage, derivatives,
or both can be packaged up into an ETF.
This makes these complex strategies
really easy to buy for anyone with a
discount brokerage account. Index ETFs
have been wildly successful. They
swallowed a ton of the assets that used
to sit in high fee actively managed
mutual funds. That has generally been a
good thing for investors, but their low
fees and the market's domination by huge
firms like Vanguard and BlackRock mean
that if you want to get into the ETF
business, you're not going to launch
another S&P 500 index fund. In both
Canada and the US, a combination of
regulatory rule changes, regulatory
approvals, and product successes has led
to the rapid proliferation of ETFs for
all kinds of investment strategies
designed to appeal to investors who want
more than an index fund. While more
product choice might sound good, this
type of innovation has a long history of
driving profits for the innovative
financial firms, often at the expense of
the end investor. The innovation we are
seeing now in my opinion is best
described as slop. Slop has come to mean
digital content of low quality that is
produced usually in large quantities by
means of artificial intelligence. I
think we're seeing something similar
with ETFs. Huge numbers of complex high
fee products that are likely to make
investors worse off rather than better.
The huge growth in ETF slop makes it
harder for investors to find good
information and choose sensible lowcost
investments for their long-term goals.
It's like trying to find a good book in
a library where someone dumped 10,000
trashy novels on top of all the
classics. The good stuff is still there,
but now it's increasingly buried under
piles of junk. I'm going to talk about
four product categories that fit into my
definition of ETF slop and explain why
most investors should probably avoid
them. The categories are thematic ETFs,
buffer ETFs, covered call ETFs, and
single stock ETFs. Each flavor of ETF
slop has its own distinct drawbacks and
appeals to different investor biases. Of
the roughly 1,000 US listed ETFs
launched in 2025, a huge portion were
leveraged ETFs, derivative income ETFs,
and defined outcome or buffer ETFs. 27%
of the new ETFs were single stock ETFs.
Derivative income ETFs took in the most
flows. Okay, let's get to the slop.
Again, I'm going to go through thematic
ETFs, buffer ETFs, covered call ETFs,
and single stock ETFs. Thematic ETFs are
funds that focus on specific trends in
the economy. A big theme in 2025 was AI,
but past examples include themes like
metaverse, crypto, clean energy,
electric vehicles, and cannabis.
Thematic ETFs capture the imaginations
of investors. Imagine how rich you will
be if you invest in the next big thing
before everyone else realizes how big
it's going to be. The problem is that
thematic ETFs tend to launch after the
theme they represent has delivered high
returns when investor interest is high
and then goes on to deliver poor
performance often resulting in the fund
closing down. Research commissioned by
the Financial Times shows that the vast
majority of thematic exchange traded
funds which enjoyed a surge in
popularity in 2025 have underperformed
broad market benchmarks. A 2021 academic
study found that thematic ETFs
underperform by 6% per year on average
in the 5 years after launching. Even
though their themes have strong
performance before launch, before
thematic ETF launches, the stocks in the
theme have usually been rising in price
and getting positive media attention.
After the ETF launches, stock prices
tend to fall back to normal levels and
media attention tends to decline. The
data in this paper suggests that
thematic ETFs launch based on themes
where investors are too optimistic and
interested. ETF companies like to launch
these funds because they can charge
higher fees and investors are eager to
buy them because they're excited about
the theme. Unfortunately, reality
doesn't match those excited
expectations. Morning Star's global
thematic fund landscape 2025 finds that
the long-term odds of picking a thematic
fund that both survives and outperforms
global equities is very low. This chart
from Morning Stars report shows that
just over 10% of thematic funds globally
outperform at the 10-year horizon. The
data for Canadian listed funds is even
more damning with 100% of Canadian
listed thematic funds either closing or
underperforming at the 10-year horizon
and 100% of funds closing by the 15-year
mark. The underlying reasons for this
poor performance are something I've gone
into a lot of detail on in other videos.
I'll link to them in the video
description. The short version is that
all the exciting growth you expect from
a theme is usually already reflected in
high stock prices for stocks related to
that theme. As reality unfolds,
expectations tend to settle down and
stock prices tend to fall. Cannabis was
a crazy extreme example. When Canada
legalized cannabis, investors saw the
potential for a massive market to open
up and they piled dollars into thematic
funds built around that cannabis theme.
At the peak, cannabis funds made up more
than 60% of the Canadian thematic fund
market. Today, they make up only 1.4%.
The hot themes today based on fund flows
are security and AI. I'm not saying we
should expect the cannabis level bad
outcome for these themes which are
obviously much different and more
consequential to the broader economy.
But I do think it's important to
consider the long-term data on thematic
investing. Despite the data, investors
continue to be attracted to these
products likely due to attentional bias.
Investors are attracted to basically
shiny objects and fund managers know
which objects are shiny and optimism
bias. Investors overestimate the
probability of a good outcome. Also
extrapolation bias investors assume that
recent trends like recent past
performance will continue indefinitely.
As a general rule, I think thematic
funds belong in the pile of ETF slop
which should be avoided by most
investors most of the time. If thematic
ETFs play on investors optimism and
extrapolative beliefs, buffer ETFs play
on their pessimism. Investors tend to
overestimate the probability of negative
events and also loss aversion. Investors
feel the pain of losses more acutely
than the joy of gains. Buffer ETFs are
funds marketed as providing exposure to
the stock market with some level of
downside protection to smooth out the
ride. I'm only picking on Beimo here
because they have the clearest marketing
material that I could find. So, great
job Beimo and apologies for picking on
you. Let's take the Beimo US equity
buffer hedged to Canadian dollars ETF
January as an example. This ETF is
designed to offer the return of a US
large cap equity index up to a cap of
8.1% for the period January 20th, 2025
through January 5th, 2026 while
providing a buffer against the first 15%
of a decrease in the market price of the
index. This structure with a capped
upside and a partial cap on the downside
is one of the most common structures for
buffer funds. Here's the Beimo fund I
mentioned against a Beimo ETF of the
underlying equity over its current
target outcome period. It has clearly
done its job of capping downside up to a
15% loss and capping upside at 8%. It's
pretty cool financial engineering for
the end user of the product if they want
that very specific payoff profile. But
this setup comes with some problems as
detailed in the 2025 paper rebuffed an
empirical review of buffer funds. The
options used to structure the payoff may
be naturally too expensive. The
transaction costs of trading options may
be high and the fees managers charge may
be meaningfully higher than they would
alternatively be in a passive allocation
to the reference asset. The authors of
rebuffed show that this has become a
huge category measured by assets and
number of funds. They also show
consistent with my ETF slop thesis that
the fees are high. With the BEIMO fund
as an example, the fund has an ME of
0.73% compared to 0.09% for the
reference asset. The paper shows that
the vast majority of buffer funds in the
sample, which includes all US listed
defined outcome funds in the morning
star database with at least 24 months of
history, offer inconsistent downside
protection with realized losses
frequently exceeding what investors
might expect based on option payoff
diagrams in marketing materials,
especially outside the narrowly defined
target outcome periods. And probably the
most important finding is that simple,
lowcost alternatives like mixing
equities with cash generally outperform
buffer funds on average. and even in
draw downs. This raises the obvious
question of whether these buffer ETFs
are truly designed to serve investor
goals or just to cater to their
behavioral biases to sell high fee
products. The authors conclude that
their analysis adds to a growing body of
evidence that much of the innovation in
this space is superficial and engineered
more for sales than for substance. I
think Buffer ETFs are really interesting
pieces of financial engineering. They
are absolutely brilliant from a
marketing perspective since they cater
to strong investor biases that many
people are willing to pay to address. I
mean, who doesn't want shock absorbers
in their portfolio? But I do not think
they improve expected outcomes for
investors after their relatively high
fees and implementation costs. They are
likely to be detrimental to long-term
investors in most cases. If someone
thinks they need buffer ETFs in their
portfolio to sleep at night, it's
probably a sign they should review their
asset allocation, which can be expressed
using a combination of lowcost index
funds or a risk appropriate asset
allocation index fund rather than adding
a complex product with high fees to
their portfolio. Unlike a buffer ETF,
covered call ETFs and the covered call
concept more generally cap upside
returns without offering meaningful
downside protection. They do this by
selling call options on stocks held by
the fund. If the underlying stocks
perform well, the upside is capped. If
they do poorly, there's limited downside
protection from the option premium, but
the downside is mostly unprotected. I
did a series of three videos on covered
calls last year, so I'm not going to go
too deep here, but the important points
are that these funds are designed to
attract investors with their high
distribution yields, which are often
enormous. The funds are marketed on
those high yields with branding names
often including the word yield or
income. But the problem is that I don't
think investors understand that the high
distribution yield from covered call
ETFs comes with a huge trade-off on the
upside of returns. The total returns of
covered call strategies should be
expected mechanically to trail the total
returns of their underlying equities. In
past videos, I compared covered call
funds to their underlying equities and
found as expected that they underperform
most of the time, including for
investors who need income from their
portfolio. As a follow-up to the many
comments on one of these videos, I
tested funds that viewers told me were
better than the ones I looked at in my
initial video. They still look the same,
not so great relative to the underlying.
I modeled an investor who needs income
from their portfolio and asked if
covered call funds provide an advantage
over a simple combination of regular
portfolio dividends that you get from
owning an index fund and occasional
portfolio sales to fund whatever the
income need is. And I found that covered
call funds leave investors worse off
rather than better. I also showed that a
simple combination of stocks and cash
can closely match the returns of a
covered call fund without putting a hard
cap on upside returns. One of the things
that I learned from making videos about
covered calls is that this investment
strategy has a cultlike following.
People do not like to be told that
covered calls are not printing free
money. It's another example of a huge
marketing win for the ETF industry
that's likely to come at a substantial
cost to long-term investors buying the
products. Single stock ETFs might be the
sloppiest version of ETF slop. They're
being issued in huge numbers. They have
high fees. They're complex tools for
speculation wrapped in an easytouse
vehicle and they're being marketed to
retail investors. There are two main
types of single stock ETFs. One focuses
on positive or negative leveraged
exposure to individual stocks while the
other offers income generation through
covered calls on individual stocks. And
then some combine these two attributes
leverage and covered calls. Single stock
covered call ETFs come with all the same
issues as covered calls more generally
with the added risk of individual
stocks. They're marketed with names like
yield maximizer, yield shares, and high
income shares to appeal to the mental
accounting bias where investors separate
income and capital into different mental
accounts. The problem again is that
income generated by a covered call comes
at the cost of upside returns. The
result is yes, a high income yield and
lower expected total returns. Some
providers attempt to address these lower
expected returns by adding in leverage
to increase expected returns. A common
structure that I've seen is 25% leverage
on a single stock covered call strategy.
In this setup, you yes, you do have
higher expected returns due to the
leverage. You still have capp upside due
to the covered call and you get the more
extreme downside of a leverage position
with only a little bit of cushion from
the option premium plus the cost of
leverage. Some of these funds have
expense ratios, including the cost of
leverage, well above 1%. Let's also not
forget that you're still exposed to the
risk of the individual stock. Most
individual stocks have long-term returns
that trail the market, and many
individual stocks suffer from large
losses that they do not recover from in
their lifetimes. These issues become
more extreme when more leverage is
employed. Leverage single stock ETFs
magnify the already high volatility of
single stocks, and they come with their
own unique costs. As reported by Jeff
Tac from Morning Star, while traders may
expect to earn two times the daily
return of an individual stock when they
purchase a 2x single stock ETF, they
often get less than 2x on the upside and
more than 2x on the downside due to the
high cost of financing inside of these
funds. These costs don't show up in an
expense ratio because the leverage is
often coming from swap contracts. Rather
than paying interest explicitly, the
financing cost is baked into the price
of the contract. The result has been a
significant shortfall in returns of many
leveraged single stock ETFs relative to
their target daily returns. Between high
costs, high volatility, and the skewess
in individual stock returns, leveraged
single stock ETFs face a lot of
headwinds. A 2025 paper by Hendrickk
Besson Bender finds that longlevered
single stock ETFs issued since 2022
underperform a simple frictionless
leverage benchmark by an average of
0.79% per month. That is more than 9
percentage points per year with 0.26
percentage points attributable to the
cost of daily rebalancing and 0.53
percentage points attributed to
frictions like fees and the actual cost
of leverage over a risk-free borrowing
rate. Inverse leverage funds trail a
simple benchmark by 1.01% on average.
That is more than 12 percentage points
per year with 0.73 percentage points
attributable to daily rebalancing and
0.27 percentage points attributable to
frictions. Since the sample of live
leveraged single stock ETFs is pretty
small and pretty new, Bessenbinder
simulates leveraged single stock ETFs
for thousands of individual stocks going
back to 1974. He finds that at a
one-year horizon, a little more than 2/3
of hypothetical 3x leveraged single
stock funds underperform a simple
leverage benchmark. 61% underperform the
unleveraged total market index return.
And 56% have negative absolute returns
at the one-year horizon. The numbers are
slightly better, but still not great for
2x leveraged hypothetical funds. And in
both cases, there is a non-trivial
occurrence of total losses at the
one-year horizon. Inverse funds,
unsurprisingly, look much worse compared
to the market. As these products began
to hit the market, the SEC even issued a
warning to investors. Picking individual
stocks is risky enough without leverage.
The last thing investors need is a tool
that makes betting on or against
individual stocks easier to do while
charging them a premium for the
privilege. In general, complexity in
investment products is not a good thing.
A 2021 paper looks at the allowance and
use of derivatives, leverage, and
illquid assets by mutual funds and finds
that they are associated with poor
performance and higher risk. Simple,
lowcost products are likely the best
tools for most investors most of the
time. As John Bogle, the late founder of
Vanguard, said, "You get what you don't
pay for." Bogle also kind of called what
we're seeing in the ETF market today
back in 2015. He said, "I freely concede
that the ETF is the greatest marketing
innovation of the 21st century, but is
the ETF a great innovation that serves
investors? I strongly doubt it. In my
experience almost 64 years in the fund
industry, I've leared to beware of
investment products, especially when
they are new and even more when they are
hot." Bogle was concerned that while
there's nothing inherently wrong with
the ETF rapper, it was being used to
entice investors into exciting products
intended to be traded frequently, likely
to their detriment, while generating
high fees for the ETF issuer. Bogle was
right. We have entered the age of ETF
slop.